<!-- There doesn't seem to be a 'foreword' element similar to the
'preface' element.  Not sure what to use instead; I guess 'preface' is
the best solution for now, even though there's also a real preface in
ch00.xml. -->

<preface id="spade.foreword">

  <prefaceinfo>
    <author>
      <firstname>Gustavo</firstname>
      <surname>Aranda</surname>
    </author>
    <pubdate>Valencia, October 31, 2007</pubdate>
  </prefaceinfo>

  <title>Foreword</title>

   <para>The idea of a Jabber-based agent platform appeared one night
	at 4 A.M. when, studying the features of the Jabber architecture,
	we found out great similarities with the ones of a FIPA-compliant
	agent platform. The Jabber protocol offered a great architecture
	for agents to communicate in a structured way and solved many issues
	present when designing a platform, such as authenticating the users (the agents),
	provide a directory or create communication channels.</para>
	
	<para>We started to work on our first prototype of this Jabber-powered
		platform and within a week we had a small working proof of concept by the name
		of <emphasis>Fipper</emphasis> which eventually allowed for dumb agents to connect and communicate
		through a common jabber server.</para>
		
	<para>Since that day, things have changed a bit. The small proof of concept
		evolved into a full-featured FIPA platform, and the new <acronym>SPADE</acronym> name was coined.
		As usual, we later had to find the meaning of the beautiful acronym.
		We came up with <emphasis role="bold">S</emphasis>mart <emphasis role="bold">P</emphasis>ython multi-<emphasis role="bold">A</emphasis>gent <emphasis role="bold">D</emphasis>evelopment <emphasis role="bold">E</emphasis>nvironment,
		which sounded both good and geek enough.</para>
		
	<para>We hope you like this book and have as much fun using it as we had writing it.
	Of course we also hope that it may become useful, but that is a secondary matter.</para>


</preface>

<!--
local variables: 
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "foreword")
end:
-->
